<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <docs>https://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs>
    <title>me on Zach Stoebner | ml • neuro • kū</title>
    <link>/categories/me/</link>
    <description>Recent content in me on Zach Stoebner | ml • neuro • kū</description>
    <image>
      <title>me on Zach Stoebner | ml • neuro • kū</title>
      <link>/categories/me/</link>
      <url>https://source.unsplash.com/collection/983219/2000x1322</url>
    </image>
    <ttl>1440</ttl>
    <generator>After Dark 9.2.3 (Hugo 0.81.0)</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>Copyright &amp;copy; Zachary Stoebner. Licensed under CC-BY-ND-4.0.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Jun 2022 06:26:47 UT</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/categories/me/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>on my life</title>
      <link>/notes/life/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 23:55:47 UT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Zach Stoebner</dc:creator>
      <guid>/notes/life/</guid>
      <description>My guide to effective brand management &amp;ndash; the tenets, epiphanies, and fruits of my efforts &amp;ndash; a reflection of tasteful pride and confidence &amp;ndash; a learning policy optimized over 24 years.</description>
      <category domain="/categories/me">Me</category>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[tl;dr My guide to effective brand management &amp;ndash; the tenets, epiphanies, and fruits of my efforts &amp;ndash; a reflection of tasteful pride and confidence &amp;ndash; a learning policy optimized over 24 years.
Morning Routine My first objective for any day is to warm my brain up with a few bitesized games. Otherwise, it&amp;rsquo;s a slow process getting out of bed and motivating myself for the day because I&amp;rsquo;m not much of a morning person.
Daily:
 Wordle Octordle Chess  Occasionally:
 Sudoku Solitaire Semantle  Sudoku and Solitaire used to be daily for me but they became tedious. Semantle is more challenging to solve but lower stakes, rather lasting the whole day when I have time to guess or think of a good semantic candidate.
Tenets I&amp;rsquo;m consistently optimizing, little by little. Serendipitously, I started thinking about some of these ideas as a kid. Although steadfast adherence helps me endure sometimes, I am constantly updating and reevaluating because things change and people can do hard things&amp;hellip; such as admitting that I am wrong or that a tenet that I lived my life by up until now may not be optimal anymore.
Core  Under no circumstances will I suffer religious zealotry, homophobia, or bigotry. Empathy, kindness, forgiveness, flexibility, and adaptability are more logical and worthwhile than apathy, hate, vindictiveness, rigidity, and immutability. I am an experience- and purpose-oriented person, less of a results- and -appearance oriented person, yet I am cognizant that the latter is advantageous in some contexts. Science, engineering, and math are the most fulfilling and constant themes of my life. My family by birth is important to me. My physical fitness, diet, and mental health are intertwined and are core to who I am. In frustrating situations, stepping back mentally, and sometimes physically, often helps me see the macro-perspective to explore my best path moving forward. The most fun and approachable to building complex systems is to solve problems modularly and abstractly, starting with the small easy components in abstract terms to lay a strong foundation, understanding, toolkit, etc. from which to build the rest. For me, it all comes together with significantly less frustration if I have tools instrument my objectives.  Observations  My lifestyle is healthy, yet improvable&amp;hellip; and non-negotiable. A workout &#43; music / podcast is my critical grounding mechanism, centering meditation, and emotional balancer. I don&amp;rsquo;t have to work out every day. I like to eat chocolate and all macarons.  The two genius foods of our day: chocolate &#43; peanut butter and sea salt chocolate chip cookies.   Cutting and bulking cycles are not conducive to my mental well-being.  I like to exercise consistently, maintain my diet, and feel physically healthy all year. Almond milk and plant protein feel better to my body than cow&amp;rsquo;s milk and whey protein.   Few video games provide real value to my life as an adult, but many were critical to my growth as a youth.  But I watch battle royales on Twitch like straight men watch football. And the lessons and enjoyment gained from the rare role-playing game with a phenomenal story are valuable to me.   Brand. Marketing. Is key.  Corrigenda  I am relatively terrible at time management. I have difficulty focusing, unless I am very excited by the task at hand, even if I want to do it.  ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>about me</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jun 2021 00:24:19 UT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Zach Stoebner</dc:creator>
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description> Hi, I&#39;m Zach!  I engineer new methods to process high-dimensional signals with practical benefit in mind, particularly in magnetic resonance imaging. My research spans signal processing, deep learning, and machine perception to solve challenging problems in autonomous systems. Generally, I&amp;rsquo;m curious about AI/ML &amp;amp; neuroscience, intelligent systems &amp;amp; robotics, and optimization &amp;amp; control.
I&amp;rsquo;m an incoming Electrical and Computer Engineering PhD student at UT Austin on a Cockrell Engineering Fellowship working with Prof. Jon Tamir in the Computational Sensing and Imaging Lab. I&amp;rsquo;m currently a graduate student researcher in VISE MedICL at Vanderbilt University advised by Prof. Ipek Oguz.
Check out my projects to see what I&amp;rsquo;m working on, notes to see what I&amp;rsquo;m thinking about, and kū to see what I&amp;rsquo;m seeing!
CV GitHub LinkedIn Scholar
</description>
      <category domain="/categories/me">Me</category>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[ Hi, I&#39;m Zach!  I engineer new methods to process high-dimensional signals with practical benefit in mind, particularly in magnetic resonance imaging. My research spans signal processing, deep learning, and machine perception to solve challenging problems in autonomous systems. Generally, I&amp;rsquo;m curious about AI/ML &amp;amp; neuroscience, intelligent systems &amp;amp; robotics, and optimization &amp;amp; control.
I&amp;rsquo;m an incoming Electrical and Computer Engineering PhD student at UT Austin on a Cockrell Engineering Fellowship working with Prof. Jon Tamir in the Computational Sensing and Imaging Lab. I&amp;rsquo;m currently a graduate student researcher in VISE MedICL at Vanderbilt University advised by Prof. Ipek Oguz.
Check out my projects to see what I&amp;rsquo;m working on, notes to see what I&amp;rsquo;m thinking about, and kū to see what I&amp;rsquo;m seeing!
CV GitHub LinkedIn Scholar
 I graduated from Vandy in May 2021 with a B.S. in computer science and neuroscience, minoring in applied math. I expect to complete my M.S. in computer science, also at Vandy, in May 2022. I&amp;rsquo;m writing my thesis on a deep learning-enabled automatic segmentation system for surgical endoscopy.
I&amp;rsquo;m passionate about connecting with youth and the broader community on topics of science and engineering. During undergrad, I was a mentor in the VUSE Design Studio and served as the communications chair in my senior year. I was also a section leader &amp;amp; reviewer for the Vanderbilt Undergraduate Research Journal for natural sciences and then served as a graduate mentor. Currently, I&amp;rsquo;m serving as the community outreach chair for Out in Engineering.
Over the past couple of years, I have had the privilege to assist with courses on discrete structures, operating systems, deep learning, AI, and currently projects in ML.
 I enjoy heavy weights, friendship, kū &amp;amp; photography, hendiadys, esports, kombucha, cucumber cocktails, and sunset runs.
I am an Anglophone &amp;gt; Lusophone &amp;gt; Hispanophone &amp;gt; Francophone. I self-studied Portuguese throughout high school, then I took a crucial gap year of emotional and linguistic growth in Lisbon, Portugal.
My hometown is Austin, TX.
 I&amp;rsquo;m always open to new opportunities, especially those that align with my interests. You can contact me at &#43;1(512)547-7486 or zachary.a.stoebner@vanderbilt.edu.
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>on my goals for this site</title>
      <link>/notes/intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jun 2021 19:18:39 UT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Zach Stoebner</dc:creator>
      <guid>/notes/intro/</guid>
      <description>:answering::clarifying::tiring:</description>
      <category domain="/categories/me">Me</category>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[To inaugurate this site, I would like to outline my goals&amp;hellip; and actually celebrate the achievement.
projects:  To communicate the manifestations of my interests. To record major work that I ha e undertaken.  notes:  To collect and structure what I learn and ideate. To hopefully help and entertain weary travelers and passersby.  kū:  To share and claim My poetic imagination Each season   Catiator: A Gladiator meme ... but different  ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
