<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <docs>https://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs>
    <title>me on Zach Stoebner | ml • neuro • kū</title>
    <link>/categories/me/</link>
    <description>Recent content in me on Zach Stoebner | ml • neuro • kū</description>
    <image>
      <title>me on Zach Stoebner | ml • neuro • kū</title>
      <link>/categories/me/</link>
      <url>https://source.unsplash.com/collection/983219/2000x1322</url>
    </image>
    <ttl>1440</ttl>
    <generator>After Dark 9.2.3 (Hugo 0.81.0)</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>Copyright &amp;copy; Zachary Stoebner. Licensed under CC-BY-ND-4.0.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2022 06:08:58 UT</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/categories/me/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>on my life</title>
      <link>/notes/life/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 23:55:47 UT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Zach Stoebner</dc:creator>
      <guid>/notes/life/</guid>
      <description>Solicited often in fact, friends ask me how I run this full-time gig. How do I stay lean, build muscle, maintain my endurance, and also balance school, publish high-impact research, and play hard every weekend? These are my epiphanies that I hope will answer these questions and let the world understand these pieces of me&amp;hellip; ideally maximizing tasteful pride and confidence and minimizing self-aggrandizing narcissism.</description>
      <category domain="/categories/me">Me</category>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[  tl;dr Self-validated by his visage, another hottie offers unsolicited advice on health habits and personal success&amp;hellip; Solicited often in fact, friends ask me how I run this full-time gig. How do I stay lean, build muscle, maintain my endurance, and also balance school, publish high-impact research, and play hard every weekend? These are my epiphanies that I hope will answer these questions and let the world understand these pieces of me&amp;hellip; ideally maximizing tasteful pride and confidence and minimizing self-aggrandizing narcissism.
Life  I am very, very lucky. I am gay, very sexy, and very smart.  I do not enjoy or vibe with straight culture and do not have to endure it.   Under no circumstances will I suffer religious zealotry, homophobia, or bigotry. Empathy, kindness, forgiveness, flexibility, and adaptability are more logical and worthwhile than apathy, hate, vindictiveness, rigidity, and immutability. I am an experience-oriented person, much less of a results-oriented person. Science, engineering, and math are the most fulfilling and constant themes of my life. My family by birth is important to me. My physical fitness, diet, and mental health are intertwined and are core to who I am.  Lifestyle  My lifestyle is healthy, yet improvable&amp;hellip; and non-negotiable. A workout &#43; music / podcast is my critical grounding mechanism, centering meditation, and emotional balancer. I don&amp;rsquo;t have to work out every day. I like to eat chocolate and all macarons. Cutting and bulking cycles are not conducive to my mental well-being.  I like to exercise consistently, maintain my diet, and feel physically healthy all year.   Few video games provide real value to my life.  But I watch battle royales on Twitch like straight men watch football.    Corrigenda  I am relatively terrible at time management. I have difficulty focusing, unless I am very excited by the task at hand, even if I want to do it.  ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>about me</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jun 2021 00:24:19 UT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Zach Stoebner</dc:creator>
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description> Hi, I&#39;m Zach!  I leverage machine learning to solve challenging problems in neuroscience, computer vision, and autonomous systems. I&amp;rsquo;m currently a graduate student researcher in VISE MedICL at Vanderbilt University investigating applied ML for medical and neuroscientific data. Generally, I&amp;rsquo;m curious about AI/ML &amp;amp; neuroscience, intelligent systems &amp;amp; robotics, and optimization &amp;amp; control.
Check out my projects to see what I&amp;rsquo;m working on, notes to see what I&amp;rsquo;m thinking about, and kū to see what I&amp;rsquo;m seeing!
CV GitHub LinkedIn
Currently, I am applying to PhD programs that encourage interdisciplinary research at the intersection of my interests. Please reach out to me at &#43;1(512)547-7486 or zachary.a.stoebner@vanderbilt.edu if you would like to work together!
</description>
      <category domain="/categories/me">Me</category>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[ Hi, I&#39;m Zach!  I leverage machine learning to solve challenging problems in neuroscience, computer vision, and autonomous systems. I&amp;rsquo;m currently a graduate student researcher in VISE MedICL at Vanderbilt University investigating applied ML for medical and neuroscientific data. Generally, I&amp;rsquo;m curious about AI/ML &amp;amp; neuroscience, intelligent systems &amp;amp; robotics, and optimization &amp;amp; control.
Check out my projects to see what I&amp;rsquo;m working on, notes to see what I&amp;rsquo;m thinking about, and kū to see what I&amp;rsquo;m seeing!
CV GitHub LinkedIn
Currently, I am applying to PhD programs that encourage interdisciplinary research at the intersection of my interests. Please reach out to me at &#43;1(512)547-7486 or zachary.a.stoebner@vanderbilt.edu if you would like to work together!
 I graduated from Vandy in May 2021 with a B.S. in computer science and neuroscience, minoring in applied math. I expect to complete my M.S. in computer science, also at Vandy, in May 2022. I am writing my thesis on an automatic segmentation system that I am developing for surgical endoscopy.
I am passionate about connecting with youth and the broader community on topics of science and engineering. During undergrad, I was a mentor in the VUSE Design Studio and served as the communications chair in my senior year. I was also a section leader &amp;amp; reviewer for the Vanderbilt Undergraduate Research Journal for natural sciences and then served as a graduate mentor. Currently, I am serving as the community outreach chair for Out in Engineering.
Over the past couple of years, I have had the privilege to assist with courses on discrete structures, operating systems, deep learning, AI, and currently ML projects.
 Beyond research, I enjoy heavy weights, friendship, haiku &amp;amp; senryu, hendiadys, esports, kombucha, cucumber cocktails, and sunset runs. Occasionally, I take a good photo and write a kū to pair with it. I especially like to take shameless photoshoots of my cats, Amie and Chaussure.
I am a Lusophone &amp;gt; Hispanophone &amp;gt; Francophone. I self-studied Portuguese throughout high school, then I took a crucial gap year of emotional and linguistic growth in Lisbon, Portugal.
My hometown is Austin, TX, and I hope one day I can live there again as a scientist guiding the future of tech.
 I am always open to new opportunities, especially those that align with my interests. You can contact me at &#43;1(512)547-7486 or zachary.a.stoebner@vanderbilt.edu.
 ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>notes intro &amp; intentions</title>
      <link>/notes/intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jun 2021 19:18:39 UT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Zach Stoebner</dc:creator>
      <guid>/notes/intro/</guid>
      <description>Welcome!</description>
      <category domain="/categories/me">Me</category>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[ Catiator: A Gladiator meme ... but different  Welcome!
To inaugurate my notes, here are my intentions:
 To collect and structure what I learn and ideate. To hopefully help and entertain weary travelers and passersby.  ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
