<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <docs>https://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs>
    <title>poetry on Zach Stoebner | ml • neuro • kū</title>
    <link>/categories/poetry/</link>
    <description>Recent content in poetry on Zach Stoebner | ml • neuro • kū</description>
    <image>
      <title>poetry on Zach Stoebner | ml • neuro • kū</title>
      <link>/categories/poetry/</link>
      <url>https://source.unsplash.com/collection/983219/2000x1322</url>
    </image>
    <ttl>1440</ttl>
    <generator>After Dark 9.2.3 (Hugo 0.102.3)</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>Copyright &amp;copy; Zachary Stoebner. Licensed under CC-BY-ND-4.0.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 19:48:40 UT</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/categories/poetry/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>on hendiadys</title>
      <link>/notes/hendiadys/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jul 2021 19:43:05 UT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Zach Stoebner</dc:creator>
      <guid>/notes/hendiadys/</guid>
      <description>I bet you have no idea what this is. You&amp;rsquo;ve definitely seen one before&amp;hellip; but you just didn&amp;rsquo;t know it. Boo!</description>
      <category domain="/categories/create">Create</category>
      <category domain="/categories/poetry">Poetry</category>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[tl;dr I bet you have no idea what this is. You&amp;rsquo;ve definitely seen one before&amp;hellip; but you just didn&amp;rsquo;t know it. Boo!
To help you understand, if these tail a structure in a sentence then it: ;) ---&gt; is, or could be formed as, a hendiadys. :&#39;( --&gt; could be confused as a possible hendiadys. However, if you were aware of the hendiadys, then go you! I&amp;rsquo;m impressed. I&amp;rsquo;ll admit that I wasn&amp;rsquo;t aware of this technique until a a couple of years ago when I was reading On Grand Strategy by John Lewis Gaddis. Gaddis covers humanity&amp;rsquo;s great leaders ;) &amp;ndash; from anitquity to modernity, in chronological order, where each chapter is devoted to one leader and their strategies ;). In the chapter on Queen Elizabeth, in many of her political letters, particularly those to King Philip of Spain, her hendiadys empowered her &amp;ndash; a virgin queen who may both save her country and leave a legacy &amp;ndash; and &amp;ldquo;positioned a culture against paralysis in world that was to come.&amp;rdquo; As noted in this chapter, other masters of hendiadys include Cranmer and Shakespeare.
&amp;ldquo;Hendiadys&amp;rdquo; translates literally as &amp;ldquo;one through two&amp;rdquo; which is easy to explain but conceals the subliminal gestalt &amp;ndash; greater than the sum of its parts. In simpler words, it is the expression of two words, such as but not limited to an adjective and its noun, :&amp;rsquo;( separated by a conjunction; instead of the former only modifying the latter, they stand alone but also together, augmenting each other. One of the most classic examples is &amp;ldquo;nice and warm&amp;rdquo; ;) in lieu of &amp;ldquo;nicely warm.&amp;rdquo; The two words are separate but each contributes to the other&amp;rsquo;s meaning in context, with a cup of morning coffee for example. For me at least, the latter phrasing is far less effective than the hendiadys. If you say the two versions aloud, you may notice as well that it&amp;rsquo;s much easier to add more dramatic inflection to the hendiadys.
In poetry, these devices are incredibly powerful, adding emphasis and rhythm :&amp;rsquo;( [but maybe ;) in the right context??]. However, they trade conciseness for that effect. To a lot of people, including myself, sacrificing conciseness is risky business, especially in poetry that is necessarily brief. Many haikuists would likely advise against such a structure. Nonetheless, when it works, hendiadys&amp;rsquo; effect is devastating and beautiful ;) at least in my opinion and I use it in haiku when I feel like it.
In popular literature, rife usage of hendiadys occurs in Shakespeare&amp;rsquo;s Hamlet. Paging through it, I spotted one used by Horatio early in Act I, maybe you can find an even earlier one, or a better one. If you&amp;rsquo;ve heard of hendiadys before, then you probably heard about it when you read this play in your high school English class. Lucky you; I wish hendiadys were discussed when my class read Hamlet some odd 5 years ago.
A related device is the hendiatris, which, you guessed it, unites three words, not necessarily with a conjunction. Hendiatris are much more popular and renowned than hendiadys because they work better as catchy slogans. For example:
&amp;ldquo;Reduce, reuse, recycle&amp;rdquo; It all builds up to recycle because, by recycling, you typically are reducing and reusing&amp;hellip; unless you&amp;rsquo;re drinking a ton of LaCroix.
&amp;ldquo;Life, liberty, and the pursuit of happiness.&amp;rdquo; For you to explain to yourself; don&amp;rsquo;t @ me with an unproductive philosophical debate.
&amp;ldquo;Passion, courage of conviction, and a strong sense of self,&amp;rdquo; Elle Woods, Legally Blonde What does this even mean? The movie is iconic and in my opinion you cannot have one of these ideas without the others.
&amp;ldquo;Look on my Works, ye Mighty, and despair!&amp;rdquo; Percy Bysshe Shelley, Ozymandias If you haven&amp;rsquo;t read this brief poem, do that right the hell now. When you read this line, &amp;ldquo;my Works&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;ye Mighty&amp;rdquo; likely mean the same thing with an epic effect, then to round it off you read &amp;ldquo;despair.&amp;rdquo; At first glance, &amp;ldquo;despair&amp;rdquo; is a verb &amp;ndash; a command to the reader to know their place. However, how do you know? &amp;ldquo;Despair&amp;rdquo; could also be a noun to imply that Ozymandias&amp;rsquo; mighty works are despair embodied.
Ozymandias is one of my all-time favorites and that line in particular is possibly my favorite line in poetry, despite its not being a hendiadys. In my opinion, crafting a good hendiadys is just as tricky, and just as impressive, as crafting a good hendiatris because saying so much more with less speaks to me more. This laconic gravity in hendiadys is what draws me to haiku &amp;amp; senryu in the first place because they give the reader room to interpret all of the opened space.
References Gaddis, John L. On Grand Strategy. , 2018. Print.
hendiadys
hendiatris
Wright, G. (1981). Hendiadys and Hamlet. PMLA/Publications of the Modern Language Association of America, 96(2), 168-193. doi:10.2307/461987
Hamlet manuscript
Ozymandias by Percy Bysshe Shelley
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>on haiku &amp; senryū</title>
      <link>/notes/haiku-senryu/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jul 2021 21:54:04 UT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Zach Stoebner</dc:creator>
      <guid>/notes/haiku-senryu/</guid>
      <description>For most of my life, I&amp;rsquo;ve been writing poetry when I experience a lightbulb moment. Over time, this habit shapeshifted to mainly haiku &amp;amp; senryū, often composing sequences of 23 - 31 or more on a day out. Although they&amp;rsquo;re usually reluctant to share, the more people that I&amp;rsquo;ve met, the more I&amp;rsquo;ve discovered that also have this practice in one way or another. People are like onions; they have layers. If you peel back enough, you&amp;rsquo;ll reach the heart &amp;ndash; haiku &amp;amp; senryū are the key to mine.</description>
      <category domain="/categories/create">Create</category>
      <category domain="/categories/poetry">Poetry</category>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[For most of my life, I&amp;rsquo;ve been writing poetry when I experience a lightbulb moment. Over time, this habit shapeshifted to mainly haiku &amp;amp; senryū, often composing sequences of 23 - 31 or more on a day out. Although they&amp;rsquo;re usually reluctant to share, the more people that I&amp;rsquo;ve met, the more I&amp;rsquo;ve discovered that also have this practice in one way or another. People are like onions; they have layers. If you peel back enough, you&amp;rsquo;ll reach the heart &amp;ndash; haiku &amp;amp; senryū are the key to mine.
4 Facts 1.) Haiku &amp;amp; senryū do not have to follow the 5-7-5 syllable pattern.
In Japanese, the pattern is 5-7-5 onji but onji cannot be directly translated to “syllable” and even less so to English syllables, which are much longer. Nonetheless, many poets pay homage to 5-7-5. For example:
The hackneyed 5-7-5 pattern Entire poems in 5 or 7 syllables Asymmetric subsections of 5 or 7 syllables (e.g. first two lines are 7 syllables total and last line is 5 syllables) The closest structure in English poetry to onji is called the mora, aka a sound unit. 5-7-5 morae approximately correspond to 2-3-2 beats. I composed a haiku below and underlined each beat to demonstrate the rhythm:
hunter&#39;s hound scans the fragrant wood -- flyting dove I drift to the 2-3-2 beats method because it&amp;rsquo;s concise and maintains a prime structure &amp;ndash; 7 beats. Rule of thumb: a reader should be able to recite the poem in a single breath. Nonetheless, I sometimes don&amp;rsquo;t follow any structure at all; ultimately, it&amp;rsquo;s what sounds and feels right.
2.) Haiku &amp;amp; senryū do not have to be written in 3 lines.
Poems are visual and often times I&amp;rsquo;ll read poets that write their haiku as a single line, or space words on different lines to evoke structure. Here&amp;rsquo;s a senryū that I composed in three forms:
grey drags :: precipice of too much vs. too little grey drags :: precipice of too much vs. too little grey drags :: precipice of too much vs. too little In my opinion, the weakest structure for this senryū is the traditional 3-line one.
3.) Haiku &amp;amp; senryū should be built upon sensory images.
Haiku are intrinsically tied with nature and senryū reflect on the human condition. Both types should generate an image in the reader&amp;rsquo;s mind, often tied with emotion. The goal is to literally capture an experience that evoked an emotion so that the reader may also experience that same emotion.
A complete haiku incorporates kigo, aka &amp;ldquo;seasonal reference&amp;rdquo;. The season can be associated with the haiku either through an explicit word or inferred from the image or culture of the poem.
Check this out: Here are some of Onishi Yasuyo&amp;rsquo;s astounding senryū. This selection is considered gendai haiku, aka modern haiku that challenge tradition.
4.) Kireji, aka &amp;ldquo;cutting words&amp;rdquo;, blur the boundary between haiku &amp;amp; senryū.
Haiku &amp;amp; senryū often have kireji in the first or second line, which pivot the poem in a related, but new, direction. In English, poets sometimes denote them with punctuation. Kireji make two from one by splitting the poem into two ideas, either through the first two lines, the last two lines, or even both! If you look closely, the middle line of the poem separately relates to each of the first and last line but also connects them when they might otherwise stand apart.
As I&amp;rsquo;ve experimented with haiku &amp;amp; senryū, I&amp;rsquo;ve found that they are not necessarily mutually exclusive. What counts as haiku to one person may in face sound more like senryū to another, depending on the image it stirs in each. The way I see it: they are the two poles of a spectrum. Take the poem below for example:
noon’s sidelight -- fall of the weighty screw wasted again Is the screw wasted because, while I was building, it fell somewhere unreachable, or am I wasted at noon?? Up to you, chat.
History Matsuo Basho is considered the first haiku master The term &amp;ldquo;haiku&amp;rdquo; was coined in the 19th century by poet Masaoka Shiki Haiku was originally the opening 3 lines of renga Renga is a party poem where you go around a circle and each person crafts a stanza that logically follows from the previous stanza The opening stanza is a haiku, called a hokku in this context The closing stanza is two lines of 7 onji, called a geku Tanka = hokku &#43; geku Tanka was the form often used in samurai death poems and consists of 5 lines totaling 31 syllables, usually reflecting on the beauty of life and the environment Predecessors of waka have roots in ancient Chinese and Korean verse. (Good) References Higginson, William J., and Penny Harter. The Haiku Handbook: How to Write, Teach, and Appreciate Haiku. Kodansha USA, 2013. Gurga, Lee, and Scott Metz. Haiku 21: an Anthology of Contemporary English-Language Haiku. Modern Haiku Press, 2011. Adam L. Kern. The Penguin Book of Haiku. Penguin UK, 2018. Matsuo, Bashō, et al. Basho: the Complete Haiku. Kodansha International, 2008. Gendai Haiku Collection Blog: The Art of Haiku Blog: Becoming a Haiku Poet ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
