<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <docs>https://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs>
    <title>spring on Zach Stoebner | ECE PhD @ UT Austin</title>
    <link>/tags/spring/</link>
    <description>Recent content in spring on Zach Stoebner | ECE PhD @ UT Austin</description>
    <image>
      <title>spring on Zach Stoebner | ECE PhD @ UT Austin</title>
      <link>/tags/spring/</link>
      <url>https://source.unsplash.com/collection/983219/2000x1322</url>
    </image>
    <ttl>1440</ttl>
    <generator>After Dark 9.2.3 (Hugo 0.102.3)</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>Copyright &amp;copy; Zachary Stoebner. Licensed under CC-BY-ND-4.0.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 18:36:18 UT</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/spring/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>spring-summer 2023</title>
      <link>/kus/spring-summer-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2024 03:58:46 UT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Zach Stoebner</dc:creator>
      <guid>/kus/spring-summer-2023/</guid>
      <description>fighting for my life, from my desk to the Uintas</description>
      <category domain="/categories/haiku">Haiku</category>
      <category domain="/categories/senryu">Senryu</category>
      <category domain="/categories/tanka">Tanka</category>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[spring wave pummels sadness washes up, rot in my brain, smoke in the Texas air portends a life, disastrous storms for weeks and Ventus’ heavy sighs : taps on skylight glass summer wind tones cresting Uintas&amp;rsquo; ridge, birds court bees pine scent, citronella smoke swirls, chipmunk’s chirp me! lake in the mountains triangle, edges of dead trees salamander hunting grounds corner of my eye an eye around the corner, a wary stranger ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>spring-summer 2022</title>
      <link>/kus/spring-summer-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 03:58:46 UT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Zach Stoebner</dc:creator>
      <guid>/kus/spring-summer-2022/</guid>
      <description>final girl in the Vandy horror picture show moves to Austin</description>
      <category domain="/categories/haiku">Haiku</category>
      <category domain="/categories/senryu">Senryu</category>
      <category domain="/categories/tanka">Tanka</category>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[spring purple blooms | for the first time in years they crunch beneath my old-aged thoughts my sum of work traverses two pages :: last Tennessee spring internal forces full moon in Pisces quit deluding! summer sweet smell of white wildflowers ~«~«≈…‡…‡…‡ blue moons eclipse at an angle then move away birds flock to cedar leaves, one last go air hums in cosmic threads at midnight ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>spring-summer 2021</title>
      <link>/kus/spring-summer-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Oct 2021 04:07:42 UT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Zach Stoebner</dc:creator>
      <guid>/kus/spring-summer-2021/</guid>
      <description>end of undergrad and feeling like the end is in sight</description>
      <category domain="/categories/haiku">Haiku</category>
      <category domain="/categories/senryu">Senryu</category>
      <category domain="/categories/tanka">Tanka</category>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[spring dogwoods wish petals sending warm love &amp;ndash; ambient footsteps first crop &amp;ndash; gradually startles a Conscience dreams of farms and glory sweaty sinews; love’s rhythm two days in a row battle, good and evil no grey in community past shame some how withers I harden first world problem is privilege knowing life ends well how long? my child trains dimensions filtered &amp;hellip; unfiltered filter summer My cats, Amie (left) and Chaussure (right). dogwood blooms &amp;ndash; love each other, overflowing the edge of the pond residential concrete crow caws to robin unfenced front yard words light the gas doubt billows from the subcortex &amp;ndash; gloom sizzles inside cloudy waves their turbulent serenity reflecting lifetime serotonin spurs inspiration &amp;hellip; for sunburnt shoulders Haiku summer &amp;ndash; Reading poet’s names A big world building your own website = pure ontology atop a slant there is the hospital storm &amp;hellip; pending binary songbird : leaps from signpost to branch on leeward gust city’s peace : my father’s infinite chagrin vanishes phone eats first the simple dishes are rarely bland ball moss&amp;hellip; between my fingertips springs trickle image search is mother of us all &amp;ndash; in a desolate scape heat in the shade &amp;ndash; cocktail opposed to coffee shunning me again pixel rain falling to a dubstep beat L, L L hacking away at wood and python also my forehead poems are my spells cast away free chilly morning dew : shapes the river valley crescent of clouds summer eve &amp;ndash; together on the wood the taste of sambal warmth of coffee at the Korean market a heartfelt friend sister and brother : mother is kind rectress teaching her sun ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>spring-summer 2020</title>
      <link>/kus/spring-summer-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Aug 2021 00:05:50 UT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Zach Stoebner</dc:creator>
      <guid>/kus/spring-summer-2020/</guid>
      <description>trip to Portland into Pandemia</description>
      <category domain="/categories/haiku">Haiku</category>
      <category domain="/categories/senryu">Senryu</category>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[spring gods falling from the sky &amp;ndash; water rushes spring mother : carried bags of groceries her sun babies my spirit animal found his heavenly rest : the spring robin the green samurai &amp;ndash; nears me with day light and his stone summer equivocation : to some I’m “weird,” or even “cool” those words mean nothing ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>spring-summer 2019</title>
      <link>/kus/spring-summer-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jul 2021 18:28:40 UT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Zach Stoebner</dc:creator>
      <guid>/kus/spring-summer-2019/</guid>
      <description>a year into my relationship</description>
      <category domain="/categories/haiku">Haiku</category>
      <category domain="/categories/senryu">Senryu</category>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[spring spring’s robins &amp;ndash; seeding the university soil my heart! raw bloom &amp;ndash; the stately robin regales chapter ends because nobody seems to remember what happened a sharp edge just begging to make a cut. the cold hurts summer the wildfire &amp;ndash; rays leave skin red and irradiated you have commitment lacking in dialogue : or so he said slithering sweat weaves from tree to tree : spotted light lone zinnia against the mad king he stands so tall ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>spring-summer 2018</title>
      <link>/kus/spring-summer-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 21:57:10 UT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Zach Stoebner</dc:creator>
      <guid>/kus/spring-summer-2018/</guid>
      <description>first-year at Vandy, early in my relationship</description>
      <category domain="/categories/tanka">Tanka</category>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[spring fatalidade -- pelo pecado puro e decepção verde fatality -- by the pure sin and green deception urbano crescimento -- humano cidades construídos em cima de outras urban development -- human cities built on others summer window beams &amp;ndash; eggs rest on rice caving in My chest crumbles with anxiety Waiting to board their flight ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
