<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <docs>https://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs>
    <title>Portuguese on Zach Stoebner | ECE PhD @ UT Austin</title>
    <link>//localhost:1313/tags/portuguese/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Portuguese on Zach Stoebner | ECE PhD @ UT Austin</description>
    <image>
      <title>Portuguese on Zach Stoebner | ECE PhD @ UT Austin</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/tags/portuguese/</link>
      <url>https://source.unsplash.com/collection/983219/2000x1322</url>
    </image>
    <ttl>1440</ttl>
    <generator>After Dark 9.2.3 (Hugo 0.152.2)</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>Copyright &copy; Zachary Stoebner. Licensed under CC-BY-ND-4.0.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 22:40:42 UT</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="//localhost:1313/tags/portuguese/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>kū português</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/kus/portugues/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jun 2021 00:24:19 UT</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>Zach Stoebner</dc:creator>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/kus/portugues/</guid>
      <description>seja alfacinha quem for</description>
      <category domain="//localhost:1313/categories/haiku">Haiku</category>
      <category domain="//localhost:1313/categories/senryu">Senryu</category>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[
dia quente, raro -- surpreedente em Cascais que não atrevem nadar rare, hot day -- surprising in Cascais that they don't dare swim champô aguado passo do pente pelo cabelo e chove bate a janela watery shampoo comb passes through hair and rain batters the window ondas do Tejo relaxam-me nas costas -- ventos até inverno waves of the Tejo relax me on my back -- winds to winter ventos frios acima : metais bem empregados atrás da faixa amarela cold winds above : well-employed metals behind the yellow line fumo aqui escrito no prédio : nuvens em tudo smoke here written on the building : clouds everywhere bebo do tinto enquanto olho ao branco -- Camões vacia I drink from red while looking at white -- empty Camões porém ao ver o pássaro procura na telha cinzas but upon seeing the bird search on grey tiles táxi busca gajo taxi pick up guy café tenho de o derrotar -- a primavera já coffee I have to defeat it -- spring now medusa azul nade à casa inverno vem blue jellyfish may swim home winter comes Press play below for the "medusa azul" gif! ]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
